Finding aid for the Eadweard Muybridge photographs LSC.1979
UCLA Library Special Collections
Eadweard Muybridge photographs
1872, 1875-1876
UCLA Library Special Collections
Muybridge, Eadweard
LSC.1979
4 linear feet (4 oversize flat boxes)
Eadweard Muybridge was a British photographer who spent much of his working life living in California and travelling in other parts of the U.S. and western Northern America. The collection consists of 46 albumen prints. Thirty-nine were taken by Muybridge in 1872 of Yosemite Valley, the Sierra Nevada Mountains, and the Mariposa Grove; seven photos were taken in Central America in 1875-1876.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Central American photos were purchased from H. L. Hoffenberg, art dealer, New York City in January, 1984.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9982939183606533
Biography/History
Born Edward James Muggeridge in Kingston-upon-Thames, England, April 9, 1830, Eadweard Muybridge came to the U.S. in the summer of 1850 and opened a bookstore in San Francisco in 1955. After being seriously injured in a fall from a stagecoach, he returned to England, where he turned to photography. He came back to San Francisco in 1866 and did photographic work for the U.S. coast and Geodetic Survey.
Muybridge achieved great fame through his photographic studies of animal and human locomotion. His studies began in 1872 when he was hired by railroad magnate Leland Stanford to prove that all four hooves of a horse left the ground during a trot. In the course of these studies, he invented devices to trip the shutters of a series of cameras to record animals in motion. He later developed a viewer called the zoopraxiscope, which allowed runs of motion photographs to be seen as if moving. These projects are now considered the forerunners of modern motion pictures.
Muybridge was known for the wide variety of photos he took of scenes in California and western North America. These included stereo views of Alaska, Canada, California cities, Yosemite Valley, Mexico, and Central America. He gained notoriety in 1874 when he murdered his wife's lover and was acquitted of the crime in a much publicized trial.
Born Edward James Muggeridge, he changed his name several times early in his U.S. career. First he changed his forenames to the Spanish equivalent Eduado Santiago. His surname appears at times as Muggridge and Muygridge, possibly due to misspellings, and Muybridge from the 1860's on. In the 1870's, he changed his first name to Eadweard, to match the spelling of King Edward, as shown on the plinth of the Kingston coronation stone. His name remained Eadweard Muybridge for the rest of his career, although his gravestone bears a further variant, Eadweard Maybridge. In the 1860's and 1870's, he also used the pseudonym Helios (Greek god of the sun), to sign many of his photographs. Helios was also the name of his studio, as well as the middle name of his only son, Florado Muybridge, born in 1874. Muybridge died in Kingston-upon-Thames on May 8, 1904.
Scope and Content
The collection is an incomplete set (39 of 51) of mammoth plate sepia albumen prints taken by Muybridge in 1872 and published in subsequent years by Bradley & Rulofson, 429 Montgomery Street, San Francisco. Thirty-four of the scenes are of the Yosemite Valley, four are of the Sierra Nevada Mountains, and one is of the Mariposa Grove of mammoth trees. The Yosemite set is made up of prints made directly from his glass plate negatives and is mounted on cardboard; the prints are numbered by the photographer. There are also seven photos taken in Central America in 1875-1876.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Yosemite photos, 1872
Central American photos, 1875-1876
Related Material
In Collection #2050 Stereoscopic Views, there are five stereoscopic views of State Prison at San Quentin (#1603), Piute Chief's Lodge (#1574, from The Indians of California Series), and three photos of the State Asylum for the Dear and Dumb and Blind; Berkeley (Looking East #1767, West Front #1768, Pupils in the Chapel #1772 from the California Series).
Related Items Available Online
Related material to this collection has been digitized and is available online: Yosemite photographs by Muybridge (TR16.8 .M987y).
Yosemite Valley (Calif.) -- Photographs.; Sierra Nevada (Calif. and Nev.) -- Photographs.; Central America -- Photographs.; albumen prints
- Series 1: Yosemite
  - Tutokanula. Valley of the Yosemite. (The Great Chief) "El Capitan" Reflected in the Merced. No. 11., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Valley of the Yosemite, From Moonlight Rock. No. 1., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Tokoya and Hunto. Valley of the Yosemite. (TheBasket.) (The Watching Eye.) No. 24., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Falls of the Yosemite, (Great Grizzly Bear) 2000 Feet Fall. No. 23., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Falls of the Yosemite. Confluence of the Merced and Yosemite Creek. No. 21., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 1/2" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Valley of the Yosemite. From Sandy Run. No. 18., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Valley of the Yosemite. From Sandy Flat. No. 17., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Sylvan Bar, Valley of the Yosemite. No. 16., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Cottonwood Bend. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 15., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - The PomPoms, Valley of the Yosemite. The Jumping Frogs Reflected. No. 13., 1872.; 17" x 21" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Tutokanula. Valley of the Yosemite. The Great Chief. "El Capitan" 3500 Feet High. No.9., 1872.; 21 3/7" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Cathedral Spires. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 8., 1872.; 17" x 21 1/2" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Cathedral Rocks. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 7., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Pohona. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 6., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Tutokanula. Valley of the Yosemite. The Great Chief. "El Capitan" 3500 Feet High. No. 5., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Loya, Valley of the Yosemite. (The Sentinel) 3570 Feet high. No. 14., 1872.; 21 3/8" on 16 7/8" x 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 1)
  - Glacier Rock. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 27., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Valley of the Yosemite, From Union Point. No. 33., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8"on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Mirror Lake. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 25., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - The Old Piute. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 26., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Glacier Channers. Valley of the Yosemite. From Panorama Rock. No. 41., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Cap of Liberty. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 31., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Helmet Dome and Little Grizzly Fall. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 42., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Pi-Wi-Ack. Valley of the Yosemite. (Shower of Stars) "Vernal Falls" 400 Feet Fall. No. 29., 1872.; 16 3/4" x 21 3/8" on 28 1/4" x 22 3/8" (Box 2)
  - Cloud's Rest. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 40., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - The High Sierra, From Glacier Rock. No. 38., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - The Domes. Valley of the Yosemite. From Glacier Rock. No. 37., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 28 1/4" x 22 3/8" (Box 2)
  - Falls of the Yosemite. From Glacier Rock. (Great Grizzly Bear) 2600 Feet Fall. No. 36., 1872.; 17" x 21 3/8" on 28 1/4" x 22 3/8" (Box 2)
  - Tenaya Canyon. Valley of the Yosemite. From Union Point. No. 35., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Yowiye Falls. Valley of the Yosemite. (Nevada Falls) 600 Feet Fall. No. 32., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Wild Cat Fall. Valley of the Yosemite. No. 30., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Tisayae. Valley of the Yosemite. (Guardian Spirit.) "Half Dome" 2750 Feet High. No. 43., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 2)
  - Yosemite Creek. Summit of Falls at Low Water. No. 44., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Yosemite Cliff. At Summit of Falls. No. 45., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17 1/8" on 22 3/8' x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Lake Tenaya. Sieera Nevada Mountaions. No.46., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Mount Hoffmann, Sierra Nevada Mountains. From Lake Tenaya. No. 48., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Temple Peaks, Sierra Nevada Mountains. No. 49., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 7/8" on 22 3/8" x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Monastery Peaks, Sierra Nevada Mountains. No. 50., 1872.; 21 5/8" x 17" on 22 3/8 x 28 1/4" (Box 3)
  - Wm. H. Seward. 85 Feet in Circumference. Mariposa Grove of Mammoth trees.No. 51., 1872.; 21 3/8" x 16 3/4" on 22 3/8" x 281/4" (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Photographer is in the picture
- Series 2: Central America
  - Street Scene, Mazatenango, Guatemala. #4423., 1875-18761875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
  - Lake Atitlan, Guatemala. #4388., 1875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
  - Sea of Clouds, Volcan Auga, Guatemala. #4384., 1875-18761875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
  - Construction At Harbor, La Union, Salvador. #4297., 1875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
  - Harbor Scene, Corinto, Nicaragua. #4293., 1875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
  - An Old Bridge Near the Beach, Panama. #4267., 1875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)
    Sepia albumen print on very thin paper
  - Coffee Harvest, San Isidrio Plantation, Guatemala. #4455., 1875-1876.; 5 3/8" x 9" on 11" x 14" (Box 4)